The cosmos is all there is
宇宙就是这样
or ever was,
过去是这样
or ever will be
以后还是这样
Come with me.
跟我来
A generation ago,
30多年前
the astronomer Carl Sagan stood here
天文学家卡尔·萨根站在这里
and launched hundreds of millions of us
带领全世界数亿人
on a great adventure...
进行了一场历险
the exploration of the universe revealed by science.
用科学去探索宇宙的奥秘
It's time to get going again.
是时候再次探险了
We're about to begin a journey that will take us
这场即将开始的旅行会向我们展示
from the infinitesimal to the infinite,
从最微小的到无穷大的
from the dawn of time to the distant future.
从时间的开始到遥远的未来
We'll explore galaxies and suns and worlds,
我们会探索不同的世界和星系
surf the gravity waves of space-time,
在时间和空间的组合中畅游
encounter beings that live in fire and ice,
接触生活在火中和冰中的生物
explore the planets of stars that never die,
探索永恒不灭的星系
discover atoms as massive as suns
了解和恒星一样大的原子
and universes smaller than atoms.
还有比原子还小的宇宙
Cosmos is also a story about us.
这也是关于人类的故事
It's the saga of how wandering
bands of hunters and gatherers
这也是先人们对星空研究的史诗长篇
found their way to the stars,
one adventure with many heroes.
众多英雄共同谱写的史诗
To make this journey,we'll need imagination.
我们需要想象力来完成这次历险
But imagination alone is not enough
但仅靠想象力是不够的
because the reality of nature is far more wondrous
因为大自然的真实样子是超乎想象的神奇
than anything we can imagine.
This adventure is made possible
by generations of searchers
几代研究人员的努力使这次的历险成为可能
strictly adhering to a simple set of rules...
他们严格地坚持一套简单的规则
test ideas by experiment and observation,
以试验和观察结果检验观点
build on those ideas
that pass the test,
以通过检验的观点为基础
reject the ones that fail,
摒弃未通过检验的
follow the evidence wherever it leads
用证据说话
and question everything.
并对一切存疑
Accept these terms,
接受这些规则
and the cosmos is yours.
宇宙就是你的
Now come with me.
跟我来吧
Sync and corrections by n17t01
www.addic7ed.com
中文翻译 @SaltyEggPain
宇    宙
时空探险之旅
第 1 集
站立于银河系
Standing Up in the Milky Way
In this ship of the Imagination,
在这艘想象之船中
free from the shackles of space and time,
不受空间和时间的限制
we can go anywhere.
我们可以去任何地方
If you want to see where we are in space,
如果你想知道我们身处太空何处
just look out the front window.
只要看向窗外
In the dimension of time, the past lies beneath us.
以时间来说，过去就在我们脚下
Here's what Earth looked like 250 million years ago.
这就是地球2.5亿年前的样子
If you want to see the future, look up.
抬头，就可以看到未来的样子
And this is how it could appear 250 million years from now.
这就是2.5亿年后可能的样子
If we're going to be venturing out
如果我们要尝试
into the farthest reaches of the cosmos,
在极度广阔的宇宙中联系
we need to know our cosmic address,
我们需要知道自己的宇宙地址
and this is the first line of that address.
这就是我们地址的第一行
地球
We're leaving the Earth,
the only home we've ever known,
我们现在离开地球，这个我们仅有的家园
for the farthest reaches of the cosmos.
向极度宽广的宇宙进发
Our nearest neighbor, the Moon, has no sky,
我们最近的邻居，月球，没有大气层
no ocean, no life...
没有海洋，没有生命
just the scars of cosmic impacts.
只有天体撞击的伤痕
Our star powers the wind and the waves
太阳为风和浪提供能量
and all the life on the surface of our world.
为地球表面一切的生物提供能量
The Sun holds all the worlds of the solar system
整个太阳系都被太阳的引力场所包围
in its gravitational embrace, starting with Mercury...
从水星开始
...to cloud-covered Venus,
where runaway greenhouse effect
到云层覆盖的金星，失控温室效应
has turned it into a kind of hell.
把它变成一处炼狱
Mars...
火星
a world with as much land as Earth itself.
表面积和地球相近
A belt of rocky asteroids circles the Sun
一条岩石似的小行星带
between the orbits of Mars and Jupiter.
在火星和木星的轨道间围绕太阳运行
With its four giant moons
and dozens of smaller ones,
木星被四个大卫星和几十个小卫星环绕
Jupiter is like its own little solar system.
木星好像拥有自己的太阳系一般
It has more mass than
all the other planets combined.
它的质量超过所有其他行星的总和
Jupiter's Great Red Spot...
木星的大红斑
a hurricane three times the size of our whole planet
它是一个比地球大3倍的古老风暴
that's been raging for centuries.
已经存在了几百年之久
The crown jewel of our solar system, Saturn,
土星宛如太阳系中皇冠上的明珠
ringed by freeways of countless orbiting
被无数运行轨道和缓慢翻滚的雪球所环绕
and slowly tumbling snowballs...
every snowball, a little moon.
每个雪球都是一个小月亮
Uranus...
天王星
and Neptune,
还有海王星
the outermost planets,
unknown to the ancients
这颗古人未知的最偏远的行星
and only discovered after
the invention of the telescope.
直到望远镜发明后才被发现
Beyond the outermost planet,
在这最偏远的行星之外
there's a swarm of tens
of thousands of frozen worlds.
还有成千上万的冰冻世界
And Pluto is one them.
冥王星就是其中一个
Of all our spacecraft,
在我们所有的航天器中
this is the one that's traveled
farthest from home...
这是离家最远的一个
Voyager 1.
旅行者1号
She bears a message to
a billion years from now,
她承载着我们发向未来的信息
something of who we were,
关于我们是谁
how we felt
我们的体会
and the music we made.
以及我们创作的音乐
The deeper waters
浩瀚宇宙海洋中
of this vast cosmic ocean
更深层的水流里
and their numberless worlds lie ahead.
存在着数不尽的世界
From out here, the Sun may look like
just another star.
从这里看，太阳好像和其他星星并无两样
But it still exerts its gravitational hold
但它的引力场依然影响着
on a trillion frozen comets,
数万亿的冰冻彗星
leftovers from the formation of the solar system
还有太阳系中那些形成于大约50亿年前的
nearly five billion years ago.
其他所有组成部分
It's called the Oort Cloud.
我们称之为 奥尔特云
No one has ever seen it before,
nor could they,
以前从没有人见过，也不可能见过
because each one of these little worlds
因为这些天体
is as far from its nearest neighbor
与它最近的邻居之间的距离
as Earth is from Saturn.
和地球与土星的距离差不多 (12-16亿公里）
This enormous cloud of comets
encloses the solar system,
这个包含太阳系的巨大彗星云团
which is the second line
of our cosmic address.
就是我们宇宙地址的第二行
地球
太阳系
We've only been able to detect
the planets of other stars
我们有能力探测其他星系的行星
for a few decades,
也就是最近几十年的事情
but we already know
that planets are plentiful...
但是我们已经知道行星的数量是很多的
they outnumber the stars.
比恒星的数量要多得多
Almost all of them will be very different from Earth,
几乎所有的行星都和地球很不一样
and hostile to life as we know it.
不适合生物生存
But what do we know about life?
但是我们对于生物又有多少了解呢？
We've met only one kind so far.
目前我们只接触过一种
Earthlife.
地球生物
See anything?
看到什么了吗？
Just empty space, right?
只是空荡荡的太空 对吗
Human eyes see only a sliver of the light
人类的眼睛只能看到
that shines in the cosmos.
宇宙中的一丝光亮
But science gives us the power
to see what our senses cannot.
但是科技让我们可以看到肉眼无法看到的
Infrared is the kind of light made visible
夜视镜可以让我们看见红外线
by night-vision goggles.
Throw an infrared sensor across the darkness...
向黑暗中发射一个红外感应器
Rogue planet.
流浪行星
World without a sun.
不绕恒星公转的行星
Our galaxy has billions of them,
adrift in perpetual night.
我们的银河中有数十亿颗游荡在永恒的黑夜中
They're orphans, cast away
from their mother stars
在他们原本的星系诞生时的混乱中
during the chaotic birth
of their native star systems.
他们像孤儿一样失去了恒星母亲
Rogue planets are molten at the core
流浪行星有着熔岩般的内核
but frozen at the surface.
但是冰冻的表面
There may be oceans of liquid water
在这些极端区域的中间
in the zone between those extremes.
也许存在着大洋般的液体水
Who knows what might be swimming there?
谁又能知道水中生活着什么东西呢
This is what the Milky Way
looks like in infrared.
这是银河的红外线显示图
Every single dot,
not just the bright ones,
每个小点，不仅仅是那些明亮的
is a star.
都是一颗恒星
How many stars?
多少恒星？
How many worlds?
多少行星？
How many ways of being alive?
多少种生命存在的方式？
Where are we in this picture?
我们身处图片中的何处？
See that trailing outer arm?
看到那条螺旋臂了吗？
That's where we live...
我们就在那里
about 30,000 light-years
from the center.
距离中心3万光年
The Milky Way Galaxy
银河系
is the next line of our cosmic address.
我们宇宙地址的下一行
We're now a hundred thousand
light-years from home.
我们现在离家十万光年
It would take light,
the fastest thing there is,
光波，存在的速度最快的东西
a hundred thousand years
to reach us from Earth.
要花10万年才能从地球到达我们这里
This is the Great Spiral in Andromeda,
这是仙女座螺旋星系
the galaxy next door.
银河系的隔壁邻居
We call our two giant galaxies
我们将这两大星系
and a smattering of smaller ones
和一些较小的星系称为
the "local group."
本星系群
地球，太阳系，银河系，本星系群
Can't even find our home galaxy from out here.
从这里已经看不到银河系了
It's just one of thousands
in the Virgo Supercluster.
它只是室女座超星系团中的几千份之一
On this scale,
以这个比例来说
all the objects we see,
including the tiniest dots,
我们所看到的，哪怕最小的点
are galaxies.
都是一个星系
Each galaxy contains billions of suns
每个星系包含几十亿颗恒星
and countless worlds.
和数不清的行星世界
Yet, the entire Virgo Supercluster itself
然而，整个室女座超星系团
forms but a tiny part of our universe.
只是我们宇宙的一个极小组成部分
This is the cosmos
on the grandest scale we know...
这是我们已知的最大范围的宇宙
a network of a hundred billion galaxies.
一张由数以千亿的星系组成的大网
It's the last line of our cosmic address...
也是我们宇宙地址的最后一行
for now.
截止目前
地球，太阳系，银河系，本星系群
室女座超星系团，可观测宇宙
Observable universe?!
可观测宇宙
What does that mean?
什么意思
Even for us, in our
Ship of the Imagination,
即使我们在想象之船中
there's a limit to how far
we can see in space-time.
在时空中所能看到的也是有限的
It's our cosmic horizon.
这是我们的宇宙水平线
Beyond that horizon
lie parts of the universe
一部分的宇宙处于水平线之下
that are too far away.
离我们实在太遥远了
There hasn't been enough time
在仅有的时间里
in the 13.8 billion year history of the universe
在宇宙138亿年的历史中
for their light to have reached us.
光线还来不及传递过来
Many of us suspect
that all of this...
很多人猜测，所有的这一切
all the worlds, stars,
galaxies and clusters
所有的行星，恒星，星系，星团
in our observable universe...
我们的可观测宇宙中得一切
is but one tiny bubble in an infinite ocean
只是其他宇宙中得沧海一粟
of other universes...
...a multiverse.
多重宇宙论
Universe upon universe.
宇宙之上的宇宙
Worlds without end.
没有尽头的世界
Feeling a little small?
感觉很渺小吗
Well, in the context
of the cosmos, we are small.
相对宇宙来说 我们确实很渺小
We may just be little guys
living on a speck of dust,
我们或许只是生活在这浩瀚宇宙中
afloat in a staggering immensity,
漂浮的尘埃上的小不点
but we don't think small.
但我们并不坐井观天
This cosmic perspective is relatively new.
现在的宇宙论诞生并不久远
A mere four centuries ago,
our tiny world was oblivious
仅仅400年前，我们尚未认识
to the rest of the cosmos.
自身世界以外的宇宙
There were no telescopes.
那时没有望远镜
The universe was only what you
could see with the naked eye.
只能看到我们肉眼可见的部分
Back in 1599,
在1599年
everyone knew that the Sun,
planets and stars
所有人都认为太阳，行球，星星
were just lights in the sky
that revolved around the Earth,
只是环绕地球的亮光
and that we were the center
of a little universe,
我们是宇宙的中心
a universe made for us.
由上帝为我们创造的宇宙
There was only one man
on the whole planet
当时全世界只有一个人
who envisioned
an infinitely grander cosmos.
想象着一个无尽的浩瀚宇宙
And how was he spending
New Year's Eve
他是怎么度过他的公元1600年除夕？
of the year 1600?
Why, in prison, of course.
当然是在监狱里
There comes a time in our lives
生命中总有那么一天
when we first realize we're not
the center of the universe,
我们发现自己并不是宇宙的中心
that we belong to something
much greater than ourselves.
我们以外还有更广大的世界
It's part of growing up.
这就是成长
And as it happens to each of us,
每个人都会经历
so it began to happen to our civilization
我们的文明也在16世纪经历过这样的成长
in the 16th century.
Imagine a world before telescopes,
想象一下望远镜问世之前
when the universe
was only what you could see
我们只能靠肉眼观察这个宇宙
with the naked eye.
It was obvious that Earth was motionless,
很显然地球是静止不动的
and that everything in the heavens...
天空中得一切
the Sun, the Moon, the stars, the planets...
太阳 月亮 星星 星球
revolved around us... and then...
都围绕着我们运行  然后
a Polish astronomer and priest named Copernicus
一位名叫哥白尼的波兰天文学家兼牧师
made a radical proposal.
The Earth was not the center.
提出一个地球并非中心的激进假想
It was just one of the planets,
and, like them,
地球只是和其他星星一样的行星
it revolved around the Sun.
绕着太阳旋转
Many, like the Protestant reformer Martin Luther,
很多人 例如宗教改革发起人马丁·路德
took this idea as a scandalous
affront to Scripture.
认为这是对圣经的可耻侮辱
They were horrified.
他们震怒了
But for one man,
Copernicus didn't go far enough.
但是另一个人却认为哥白尼说的不全面
His name was Giordano Bruno,
他叫焦尔达诺·布鲁诺
and he was a natural-born rebel.
他生性反叛
He longed to bust out of that
cramped little universe.
他渴望打破这狭隘宇宙的枷锁
Even as a young Dominican monk in Naples,
在那不勒斯做道明会的修道士时
he was a misfit.
This was a time
他就与这个世界格格不入
when there was
no freedom of thought in Italy.
当时在意大利没有思想的自由
But Bruno hungered to know
但是布鲁诺渴望了解
everything about God's creation.
关于上帝创世的一切
He dared to read the books
banned by the Church,
他阅读了被教廷禁止的书籍
and that was his undoing.
从此踏上了不归路
In one of them,
这些书籍中
an ancient Roman, a man dead
for more than 1,500 years
有一本作者是1500年前的古罗马人
（物性论 - 卢克莱修）
whispered to him of a universe far greater,
向他描述了一个更广阔的宇宙
one as boundless as his idea of God.
广阔的犹如他的上帝一般
Lucretius asked the reader
卢克莱修让他的读者
to imagine standing
at the edge of the universe
想象站在宇宙的边缘
and shooting an arrow outward.
向外射出一支箭
If the arrow keeps going,
then clearly,
如果箭继续前进，那么很明显
the universe extends beyond
what you thought was the edge.
宇宙继续向所谓的边缘以外延伸
But if the arrow doesn't keep going...
但是如果箭不继续前进
say it hits a wall...
then that wall must lie
比方说 撞在一堵墙上
beyond what you thought
was the edge of the universe.
那么墙必然是处在所谓的边缘之外
Now if you stand on that wall
and shoot another arrow,
那么如果你站在这堵墙上向外射箭
there are only the same
two possible outcomes...
也只有这相同的两个结果
it either flies forever out into space,
要么是飞入无尽的太空
or it hits some boundary
要么是撞在某个障碍物上
where you can stand and shoot
yet another arrow.
然后你又可以站在上面射出另一支箭
Either way, the universe is unbounded.
无论如何 宇宙是没有界限的
The cosmos must be infinite.
宇宙必然是无尽的
This made perfect sense to Bruno.
布鲁诺深以为然
The God he worshiped was infinite.
他崇拜的上帝是全能的
So how, he reasoned, could
Creation be anything less?
所以他断定 上帝创造的宇宙怎会不是无穷
It was the last steady job he ever had.
那是他的最后一份稳定工作
And then, when he was 30,
后来 当他30岁时
he had the vision that sealed his fate.
他的一个幻觉从此改变他的一生
In this dream, he awakened to a world
在这个梦中 他认识到了
enclosed inside a confining bowl of stars.
一个包含在一群行星中的世界
This was the cosmos of Bruno's time.
就是他那个时代的宇宙
He experienced a sickening moment of fear,
他感到一阵不舒服的害怕
as if the bottom of everything
就像脚下的一切
was falling away beneath his feet.
向下坠落
But he summoned up his courage.
但是他鼓起了勇气
I spread confident wings to space
我展开自信的翅膀飞向太空
and soared toward the infinite,
leaving far behind me
向上高飞至无尽的天空
what others strained to see
from a distance.
将一切的压力抛在身后
Here, there was no up, no down, no edge,
这里没有上 没有下 没有边界
no center.
没有中心
I saw that the Sun
was just another star,
我看见太阳和其他星星一样
and the stars were other Suns,
each escorted by other Earths
还有其他被行星伴随着的恒星
like our own.
就像我们的太阳
The revelation of this immensity was like
这巨大的启示对他就如同
falling in love.
坠入爱河
Bruno became an evangelist,
布鲁诺变成了一个传教士
spreading the gospel
of infinity throughout Europe.
他在欧洲各地宣扬他的宇宙无限论
He assumed that other lovers
of God would naturally embrace
他以为其他上帝的追随者会同样接受
this grander and more glorious view of Creation.
这个对于创世的伟大并荣耀的观点
What a fool I was.
我太傻了
He was excommunicated
在他的祖国 他被罗马天主教会开除教籍
by the Roman Catholic Church in his homeland,
expelled by the Calvinists in Switzerland,
他不仅被瑞士加尔文长老会驱逐出境
and by the Lutherans in Germany.
还被德国的路德教派驱逐出境
Bruno jumped at an invitation
布鲁诺接受了一份邀请
to lecture at Oxford, in England.
去英国牛津大学讲课
At last, he thought,
他认为这是一个机会
a chance to share his vision
with an audience of his peers.
可以与他类似的人分享他的观点
I have come to present
a new vision of the cosmos.
我来介绍一个对于宇宙的崭新看法
Copernicus was right to argue that our world
哥白尼是对的
is not the center of the universe.
我们的世界并不是宇宙的中心
The Earth goes around the Sun.
地球绕着太阳旋转
It's a planet, just like the others.
它和其他行星一样
But Copernicus was only the dawn.
但哥白尼只是曙光
I bring you the sunrise.
而我为你们带来日出
The stars are other fiery suns,
那些星星和我们炙热的太阳一样
made of the same substance as the Earth,
由和地球一样的天体组成
and they have their own watery earths,
他们也有自己的含水的地球
with plants and animals
no less noble than our own.
上面有着和我们一样高贵的动物植物
Are you mad or merely ignorant?
你是疯了还是太蠢
Everyone knows there is only one world.
总所周知只有一个世界
What everyone knows is wrong.
那是错误的
Our infinite God has created
a boundless universe
我们全能的上帝创造了一个无边无际的宇宙
with an infinite number of worlds.
其中包含了无数的星球
Do they not read Aristotle where you come from?
你们那的人没读过亚里斯多德的书吗
Or even the Bible?
或者是圣经吗
I beg you, reject antiquity, tradition, faith, and authority.
我请求你摒弃老旧和传统的信仰和权威
Let us begin anew,
让我们重新认识
by doubting everything we assume
质疑我们以为已经被证实的一切
- has been proven.
- Heretic!
异端者
Infidel!
异教徒
Your God is too small.
你们信仰的上帝太小了
A wiser man would have learned his lesson.
明智的人本应该从中吸取了教训
But Bruno was not such a man.
可惜布鲁诺并不是那个人
He couldn't keep his soaring
vision of the cosmos to himself,
他不停的宣扬自己观点
despite the fact that the penalty for doing so
尽管这会带来沉痛的代价
in his world was the most vicious form
在他的那个时代，代价是如此的残酷
of cruel and unusual punishment.
无情和不寻常的惩罚
Giordano Bruno lived at a time when there was no such thing
焦尔达诺·布鲁诺生活的那个时代
as the separation of church and state,
没有政教分离
or the notion that freedom
of speech was a sacred right
没有言论自由神圣不可侵犯
of every individual.
Expressing an idea that didn't
conform to traditional belief
表达与传统信仰相悖的观点
could land you in deep trouble.
会带来极大的麻烦
Recklessly, Bruno returned to Italy.
布鲁诺不顾一切地回到了意大利
Maybe he was homesick.
也许是想家了
But still, he must have known
that his homeland
可是他必须知道
was one of the most dangerous
places in Europe
他的祖国对他来说
he could possibly go.
是最危险的国家
The Roman Catholic Church
maintained a system of courts
由罗马天主教会管辖的宗教法庭
known as the Inquisition,
被称为异端裁判所
and its sole purpose was to investigate and torment
它唯一职责就是审查和折磨
anyone who dared voice views that differed from theirs.
与教会持有不同声音和观点的人
It wasn't long before Bruno fell into the clutches
布鲁诺很快就被思想警察抓获
of the thought police.
This wanderer, who worshiped
an infinite universe,
这位信奉无限宇宙的流浪者
languished in confinement for eight years.
在八年的监狱生涯中饱受煎熬
Through relentless interrogations,
尽管受尽残酷的审讯
he stubbornly refused to renounce his views.
他依然不愿放弃他的观点
Why was the Church willing
为什么教会要花
to go to such lengths to torment Bruno?
如此长的时间来折磨布鲁诺
What were they afraid of?
他们在害怕什么
If Bruno was right, then the sacred books
如果布鲁诺是对的 那么这些圣典
and the authority of the Church
还有教会的权威
would be open to question.
都会受到质疑
Finally, the cardinals of the Inquisition
最终 异端裁判所的红衣主教们
rendered their verdict.
做出了他们的判决
You are found guilty
你有罪
of questioning the Holy Trinity
你质疑圣父圣子圣灵三位一体
and the divinity of Jesus Christ.
你质疑耶稣基督的神威
Of believing that God's wrath is not eternal,
你相信上帝的怒火不会永远
that everyone will be saved.
所有人都会被宽恕
Of asserting the existence of other worlds.
你断言其他世界存在的主张
All of the books you have written
你写的所有书
will be gathered up and burned in St. Peter's Square.
都会在圣彼得广场前焚毁
Reverend Father, these eight years of confinement
尊敬的大人 8年的监禁
have given me much time to reflect.
给了我很多时间去反省
So...
然后呢
you will recant?
你要放弃你的主张吗
My love and reverence for the Creator
我对造物主的爱和崇敬
inspires in me the vision of an infinite Creation.
激发我对全能的上帝的认识
You shall be turned over to the Governor of Rome
你会被移交到罗马总督
to administer the appropriate punishment
予以执行相应地惩罚
for those who will not repent.
如果你拒不忏悔的话
It may be that you are more afraid
可能你宣布这个判决时的恐惧
to deliver this judgment than I am to hear it.
比我听到判决的时候更厉害
Ten years after Bruno's martyrdom,
布鲁诺殉难的10年后
Galileo first looked through a telescope,
伽利略通过望远镜
realizing that Bruno had been right all along.
发现布鲁诺的学说确实没错
The Milky Way was made of countless stars
银河系是由肉眼看不到的无数恒星组成
invisible to the naked eye,
and some of those lights in the
sky were actually other worlds.
天空中的某些光亮其实是其他的行星
Bruno was no scientist.
布鲁诺不是科学家
His vision of the cosmos was a lucky guess,
他只是侥幸猜中了
because he had no evidence to support it.
因为没有证据支持他
Like most guesses, it could
well have turned out wrong.
就和其他猜想一样 也有可能不对
But once the idea was in the air,
但是这个观点一旦散播出去
it gave others a target to aim at.
它就给了其他人一个方向
If only to disprove it.
哪怕只是为了反驳
Bruno glimpsed the vastness of space.
布鲁诺大致理解了太空的浩瀚无垠
But he had no inkling of the
staggering immensity of time.
但他对于时间的惊人无际没有丝毫概念
How can we humans, who rarely
live more than a century,
寿命很少超过一个世纪的普通人
hope to grasp the vast expanse of time
怎么可能去理解宇宙的历史
that is the history of the cosmos?
就像浩瀚宽阔的时间长河
The universe is 13.8 thousand million years old.
宇宙诞生于138亿年前
In order to imagine all of cosmic time,
为了更好地想象宇宙的历史
let's compress it into a single calendar year.
我们把它压缩成12个月的年历
The cosmic calendar begins on January 1st
with the birth of our universe.
年历上的1月1号是宇宙诞生的日子
It contains everything that's
happened since then,
年历上包含了从那以后经历的所有时间
up to now,
一直到现在
which on this calendar
is midnight December 31st.
在这个年历上的12月31号午夜
On this scale, every month
represents about a billion years.
按照这个比例 每个月代表10亿年
Every day represents nearly 40 million years.
每天代表将就4千万年
Let's go back as far as we can,
让我们尽可能地回到过去
to the very first moment of the universe.
回到宇宙最开始的时刻
January 1st, the Big Bang.
1月1号 宇宙大爆炸
It's as far back as we can see in time...
这是我们所能看到最早的时间
for now.
目前而言
Our entire universe emerged from
a point smaller than a single atom.
整个宇宙形成于一个比原子还小的点
Space itself exploded in a cosmic fire,
空间在密度极大温度极高的状态下爆炸
launching the expansion of the universe
由此开始了宇宙的扩张
and giving birth to all the energy
并诞生了所有的能量
and all the matter we know today.
已经产生所有我们已知的事物
I know that sounds crazy,
听上去很疯狂
but there's strong observational evidence
但是我们有很强力的观测证据
to support the Big Bang theory.
来支持宇宙大爆炸理论
And it includes the amount
of helium in the cosmos
证据还有氦元素在宇宙中的比例
and the glow of radio waves
left over from the explosion.
以及爆炸残留的发光无线电频谱
As it expanded, the universe cooled,
爆炸后宇宙开始冷却
and there was darkness
for about 200 million years.
其间有2亿年左右的黑暗
Gravity was pulling together
clumps of gas and heating them
万有引力将气体集聚并且加热
until the first stars burst into light
直到第一批恒星发出亮光
on January 10th.
相当于1月10号
On January 13th, these stars coalesced
1月13号 这些恒星开始结合
into the first small galaxies.
形成第一批小星系
These galaxies merged to form still larger ones,
这些星系融合成更大的星系
including our own Milky Way,
包括我们的银河系
which formed about 11 billion years ago,
产生于110亿年左右
on March 15th of the cosmic year.
就是宇宙年历上得3月15号
Hundreds of billions of suns.
数千亿的恒星中
Which one is ours?
哪个是我们的太阳
It's not yet born.
此时尚未诞生
It will rise from the ashes of other stars.
它将从其他恒星的灰烬中产生
See those lights flashing like paparazzi?
看到这些犹如闪光灯般的亮光吗
Each one is a supernova,
每一个都是超新星
the blazing death of a giant star.
一颗超大恒星的耀眼爆炸
Stars die and are born
in places like this one...
恒星消亡和诞生的地方
a stellar nursery.
我们称为星星苗圃 （分子云）
They condense like raindrops
他们像雨滴般
from giant clouds of gas and dust.
从巨大的气态和灰尘云中凝结
They get so hot that the nuclei of the atoms
他们温度高的可以把原子中的原子核
fuse together deep within them
融合在一起
to make the oxygen we breathe,
the carbon in our muscles,
从而产生了我们呼吸的氧气 肌肉中的碳元素
the calcium in our bones,
the iron in our blood,
骨头中的钙元素 血中的铁元素
all of it was cooked
所有的这一切都产生于
in the fiery hearts of long-vanished stars.
从此消亡的恒星炙热的内心
You, me, everyone...
你 我 所有人
we are made of star stuff.
我们都是由星辰物质组成
This star stuff is recycled and enriched,
星辰物质被不断循环和浓缩
again and again,
一遍又一遍
through succeeding generations of stars.
经过几代恒星的诞生消亡
How much longer until the birth of our Sun?
离我们的太阳诞生还有多久
A long time.
很长时间
It won't begin to shine
我们太阳的第一次发光
for another six billion years.
还要再等60亿年
Our Sun's birthday is August 31st
太阳的生日是8月31号
on the Cosmic Calendar...
在这个宇宙年历上
...four and a half billion years ago.
45亿年前
As with the other worlds of our solar system,
就像太阳系中其他行星
Earth was formed from a disk of gas and dust
地球在一堆气体和灰尘中产生
orbiting the newborn Sun.
绕着新生的太阳运行
Repeated collisions produced
a growing ball of debris.
反复的碰撞产生了一个发光的球状碎片
See that asteroid?
看到那个小行星了吗
No, not that one.
不是那个
The one over there.
那边的那个
We exist because the gravity
of that one next to it
我们的存在归功于它旁边的引力
just nudged it an inch to the left.
把它轻轻向左推了一英寸
What difference could an inch make
一英寸有很大的区别吗
on the scale the solar system?
按照太阳系的比例来说
Just wait, you'll see.
稍等 你马上就能看到
The Earth took one hell of a beating
在最初的10亿年里
in its first billion years.
地球饱受摧残
Fragments of orbiting debris collided and coalesced,
任由轨道上的碎片撞击和融合
until they snowballed to form our Moon.
直到他们形成了我们的月亮
The Moon is a souvenir of that violent epoch.
月亮是那个暴力纪元的纪念品
If you stood on the surface
of that long ago Earth,
如果你站在远古地球的表面
the Moon would have looked
a hundred times brighter.
月亮会看上去比现在亮100倍
It was ten times closer back then,
那时月亮离我们近10倍
locked in a much more intimate
gravitational embrace.
被比现在更强大的引力场吸引着
As the Earth cooled, seas began to form.
地球冷却下来 海洋形成了
The tides were a thousand times higher then.
海浪比现在高1000倍
Over the eons,
tidal friction within Earth
经过极漫长的时间 潮汐的摩擦力
pushed the Moon away.
将月球推远
Life began somewhere around here,
生命差不多在这个时候诞生
September 21st,
9月21号
three and a half billion
years ago on our little world.
在地球上的35亿年前
We still don't know how life got started.
我们依然不知道生命如何起源
For all we know,
我们只是知道
it may have come from
another part of the Milky Way.
有可能是来自银河系的其他地方
The origin of life
生命的起源
is one of the greatest
unsolved mysteries of science.
是最伟大的未知科学奇迹之一
That's life cooking,
生命的演变
evolving all the biochemical recipes
一切生物化学的进化
for its incredibly complex activities.
充满了无与伦比的复杂活动
By November 9th,
life was breathing, moving,
到了11月9号 生命开始呼吸 移动
eating, responding to its environment.
进食和对周遭环境做出反应
We owe a lot to those pioneering microbes.
多亏了这些有开拓性的微生物
Oh, yeah... one other thing.
没错 就是这些不起眼的家伙
They also invented sex.
他们还发明了繁殖
December 17th was quite a day.
12月17号 很特别的一天
Life in the sea really took off,
海洋中生命的发展开始腾飞
it was exploding with a diversity
形形色色的大型植物和动物
of larger plants and animals.
爆炸式的发展
Tiktaalik was one of the first
animals to venture onto land.
提塔利克鱼是最早冒险登陆的动物之一
It must have felt like visiting another planet.
感觉肯定像是造访另一个星球
Forests, dinosaurs,
森林  恐龙
birds, insects,
鸟类 昆虫
they all evolved in the final week of December.
都在12月的最后一周进化而来
The first flower...
第一朵花
bloomed on December 28th.
在12月28号 盛开
As these ancient forests grew and died
随着古森林的成长死亡
and sank beneath the surface,
并被深埋进地下
their remains transformed into coal.
他们的残骸形成了煤
300 million years later,
3亿年后
we humans are burning most of that coal to power
人类燃烧这些煤来推动文明的发展
and imperil our civilization.
同时也使我们的文明陷入危机
Remember that asteroid back in the formation
还记得那颗在太阳系形成时的
of the solar system...
小行星吗
the one that got nudged a little to the left?
那颗被轻轻推动的小行星
Well, here it comes.
它来了
It's 6:24 AM
早晨6点24分
on December 30th on the Cosmic Calendar.
宇宙年历上的12月30号
For more than a hundred million years,
在1亿年的时间里
the dinosaurs were lords of the Earth,
恐龙曾是这个地球的统治者
while our ancestors, small mammals,
当我们的祖先 小型哺乳动物
scurried fearfully underfoot.
战战兢兢地在地面爬来爬去的时候
The asteroid changed all that.
这颗小行星改变了一切
Suppose it hadn't been nudged at all.
假如它没有被推动
It would have missed the Earth entirely,
它会完全和地球擦肩而过
and for all we know, the
dinosaurs might still be here
恐龙恐怕依然存在
but we wouldn't.
但我们不会
This is a good example of the extreme contingency,
这是极端突发状况的好例子
the chance nature, of existence.
生存的偶然性
The universe is already more than 13 and a half
宇宙已经诞生了超过
billion years old.
135亿年
Still no sign of us.
人类仍未出现
In the vast ocean of time that this calendar represents,
在这个年历代表的时间长河中
we humans only evolved within the last hour
人类在最后一小时进化
of the last day of the cosmic year.
宇宙年历中的最后一天
11:59 and 46 seconds.
11点59分46秒
All of recorded history occupies only the last 14 seconds,
全部有记载的历史发生在最后的14秒里
and every person you've ever heard of
你听说过得所有人
lived somewhere in there.
存在于这个点的某个位置
All those kings and battles,
migrations and inventions,
所有这些国王 战役 迁徙 发明
wars and loves, everything in the history books
战争和爱情 历史书中的一切
happened here, in the last seconds
都发生在这宇宙年历中的最后几秒
of the Cosmic Calendar.
But if we want to explore
但如果我们想要研究
such a brief moment of cosmic time...
宇宙年历中这段极短的时间
...we'll have to change scale.
我们必须改变比例
We are newcomers to the cosmos.
我们是这个宇宙的新丁
Our own story only begins on the
last night of the cosmic year.
我们的历史仅仅从宇宙年的最后一晚开始
It's 9:45 on New Year's Eve.
新年前夜的9点45分
Three and a half million years ago,
350万年前
our ancestors, yours and mine, left these traces.
你我的祖先留下这些足迹
We stood up, and parted ways from them.
我们站了起来和他们区别开来
Once we were standing on two feet,
自从我们直立行走
our eyes were no longer fixated on the ground.
我们的双眼不在迷恋地面
Now we were free to look up in wonder.
现在我们可以自由的探索奇迹
For the longest part of human existence,
人类存在的大部分时间里
say the last 40,000 generations,
比方说最近的4万代人
we were wanderers,
我们曾是流浪者
living in small bands of hunters and gatherers,
猎人和采集者混住在一起
making tools, controlling fire,
制作工具 生火
naming things,
给事物起名字
all within the last hour of the Cosmic Calendar.
都发生在宇宙年历的最后一个小时里
To find out what happens next, we'll have to change scale
我们必须改变比例去继续探寻
to see the last minute of the last night
最后一晚的最后一分钟
of the cosmic year.
发生了什么
11:59
We're so very young on the time scale of the universe
以宇宙时间比例来说我们太太太年轻了
that we didn't start painting our first pictures
我们甚至还没开始画出第一张画
until the last 60 seconds of the cosmic year,
直到宇宙年历的最后60秒
a mere 30,000 years ago.
只不过是3万年前
This is when we invented astronomy.
我们发明了天文学
In fact, we're all descended from astronomers.
事实上我们都是天文学家的后裔
Our survival depended on
knowing how to read the stars
我们的生存要依靠研究星星
in order to predict the coming of the winter
用来预测冬天的到来
and the migration of the wild herds.
以及兽群的迁徙
And then, around 10,000 years ago,
然后大约1万年前
there began a revolution in the way we lived.
我们的生活方式迎来了变革
Our ancestors learned
how to shape their environment,
我们的祖先学会了如何改变周围环境
taming wild plants and animals,
栽培植物 驯养动物
cultivating land and settling down.
耕作土地 定居下来
This changed everything.
这改变了一切
For the first time in our history,
有史以来第一次
we had more stuff than we could carry.
我们可以拥有超过我们负重能力的东西
We needed a way to keep track of it.
我们需要把这些数量记录下来
At 14 seconds to midnight,
午夜前的14秒
or about 6,000 years ago, we invented writing.
大约6千年前 我们发明了书写
And it wasn't long before we started recording
随后不久我们就开始记录其他东西
more than bushels of grain.
不仅仅是粮食的数量
Writing allowed us to save our thoughts
书写让我们保存我们的想法
and send them much further in space and time.
并且跨越时间和空间的传播它们
Tiny markings on a clay tablet
泥板上的细小印记
became a means for us to vanquish mortality.
成了我们征服有限的生命的手段
It shook the world.
震撼了整个世界
Moses was born seven seconds ago.
摩西出生于7秒之前
Buddha, six seconds ago.
释迦摩尼 6秒前
Jesus, five seconds ago.
耶稣基督 5秒前
Mohammed, three seconds ago.
穆罕穆德 3秒前
It was not even two seconds ago that, for better or worse,
不到2秒前 不论好坏
the two halves of the Earth discovered each other.
地球一边的人类发现了地球的另一边
And it was only in the very last second
仅仅在最后的一秒钟里
of the Cosmic Calendar that we began to use science
我们开始使用科学
to reveal nature's secrets and her laws.
去揭示大自然的秘密和规则
The scientific method is so powerful
科学方法是如此的强大
that in a mere four centuries,
只用了4个世纪的时间
it has taken us from Galileo's first look through a telescope
就从伽利略第一次看向望远镜
at another world to leaving our footprints on the Moon.
到人类在月球上留下足迹
It allowed us to look out across space and time
它让我们可以越过时间和空间
to discover where and when we are in the cosmos.
去观察我们在宇宙时空中的位置
We are a way for the cosmos to know itself.
我们有了了解宇宙本质的办法
Carl Sagan guided the maiden voyage of Cosmos
卡尔·萨根30多年前带领我们进行了首次的
a generation ago.
宇宙航行
He was the most successful
science communicator
他不仅是20世纪最成功的
of the 20th century,
科学传播者
but he was first and foremost a scientist.
也是一位首屈一指的科学家
Carl contributed enormously
卡尔为我们了解行星
to our knowledge of the planets.
做出了极大的贡献
He correctly predicted the existence of methane lakes
他正确地预测了有沼气湖存在于
on Saturn's giant moon Titan.
木星的卫星 泰坦 土卫六上
He showed that the atmosphere of the early Earth
他指出早期地球的大气层中
must have contained powerful greenhouse gases.
必然含有强大的温室气体
He was the first to understand
that seasonal changes on Mars
他首先推断出火星上的季节变化
were due to windblown dust.
是由沙尘暴引起
Carl was a pioneer
卡尔是一位
in the search for extraterrestrial life
在探索地球以外智慧生物领域的
and intelligence.
先行者
He played a leading role in
every major spacecraft mission
太空时代的最初40年里 每次主要的
to explore the solar system during the first 40 years
太阳系探索航天任务 他都担任了
of the Space Age.
重要的职务
But that's not all he did.
这还不是全部
This is Carl Sagan's own calendar from 1975.
这是卡尔的一本1975年的记事日历
Who was I back then?
我那时在做什么
I was just a 17-year-old kid from the Bronx
我只是一个纽约的17岁男孩
with dreams of becoming a scientist,
梦想着可以成为科学家
and somehow the world's most
famous astronomer found time
世界上最著名的天文学家
to invite me to Ithaca, in upstate New York,
邀请我去纽约州
and spend a Saturday with him.
和他共度一个周六
I remember that snowy day like it was yesterday.
我记得那天下着雪
He met me at the bus stop
他来公车站接我
and showed me his laboratory at Cornell University.
带我参观了他在康奈尔大学的实验室
Carl reached behind his desk
and inscribed this book for me.
卡尔从书桌后拿出这本书并在上面为我题字
"For Neil, a future astronomer.
至 尼尔 未来的天文学家
Carl."
卡尔
At the end of the day, he drove
me back to the bus station.
结束后 他开车送我去公车站
The snow was falling harder.
雪下得更大了
He wrote his phone number...
his home phone number...
他写下他的电话号码 家里的电话
on a scrap of paper and he said,
"If the bus can't get through,
他把号码写在一张小纸片上 如果公车没有来
call me and spend the night at my home with my family."
打电话给我 就在我家过夜
I already knew I wanted to become a scientist,
我当时已经决定要当一名科学家
but that afternoon, I learned from Carl
但是那天下午 我认识到
the kind of person I wanted to become.
我要做他那样的人
He reached out to me and to countless others,
他帮助了我 还有其他很多人
inspiring so many of us to study, teach and do science.
激励我们去学习，教授，研究科学
Science is a cooperative enterprise,
科学研究是一份需要合作的事业
spanning the generations.
持续几代人的时间
It's the passing of a torch from
teacher to student to teacher,
火炬在老师和学生的手中传递
a community of minds
reaching back to antiquity
一群伟大的思想从远古
and forward to the stars.
贯穿 直至未来的星空
Now, come with me.
现在跟我来
Our journey is just beginning.
我们的旅程开始了
Sync and corrections by n17t01
www.addic7ed.com
中文翻译 @SaltyEggPain